A Guide to the Papers of Dudley Cooper and Ocean View Amusement Park 1941-1978
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Dudley Cooper and Ocean View Amusement Park 1941-1978
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 31
14 Hollinger Document Cases, 5 Oversized Boxes
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Dudley Cooper, September 5, 1978.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dudley Cooper was born in Tarboro, North Carolina in 1899. His family then moved to the Norfolk area in 1900. While a student at Maury High School, Dudley enlisted in the army when the United States entered World War I. He was trained in the Students Army Training Corps at Virginia Polytechnic Institute. At the end of the war, Dudley was discharged with the rank of sergeant and returned to complete his high school education in 1919. Dudley then attended the American Institute of Optometry, which later became an extension of Columbia University. He earned an optometry degree and returned to Norfolk.
Though he was the first college-trained optometrist to practice in Norfolk, Dudley Cooper became well known in this city chiefly through his ownership and operation of Ocean View Amusement Park. This came about in 1944 when he purchased land along the beach of Chesapeake Bay in the area now known as Ocean View. During World War II, Dudley set aside part of the land for the U.S. Army Coastal Installation, the Navy Relief Fund Raising, Naval Reserve Recruiting and various civic affair groups.
By studying the papers in the collection he donated to the Old Dominion University Archives, researchers can get an idea of the details involved in owning and operating a large amusement park. While still setting up Ocean View Park, Dudley Cooper was approached by three Black professional men: a dentist, a lawyer, and a high school principal. They wanted his help in establishing a special amusement park for the Black community. Dudley helped these men establish Seaview Beach Amusement Park, also on the Chesapeake Bay, which operated until 1966.
Dudley Cooper was active in civic and service organizations on both a local and national level. He was instrumental in bringing the 1937 National Conference of Christians and Jews to Norfolk, a meeting that led to the establishment of the annual Brotherhood Week. He was selected by the Armed Services Committee to serve as chairman of the Jewish USO in Norfolk and continued thus for the duration of the War.
After the war, Dudley served as chairman of the Norfolk United Jewish Appeal, and in 1947 was responsible for doubling the previous highest contribution ever received. Dudley and his wife, Mary, were also among the many American Jews who aided the European Jewish refugees of the steamboat Exodus by signing affidavits that allowed their entry into this country. Other activities include a local campaign begun by Dudley in the late forties known as "Cooper's Crusade" which eventually replaced Norfolk's antiquated street car system with a publicly-owned bus system. He also aided the journalistic education of young newspaper reporters with the foundation of the Norfolk Newspaper Guild Scholarship Fund. Dudley's civic and charitable activities continued throughout his life. At the same time he operated an optometrist's practice and successful amusement parks. In 1975 Dudley received the Distinguished Service Award from the Arnold Basmey Lodge No. 1195 of B'nai B'rith in recognition for his past leadership in Norfolk business and community affairs.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Dudley Cooper are primarily concerned with the operation of Ocean View Park. This collection is divided into seven series: Correspondence, Legal Documents, Financial Papers, Printed Material, Photographs, Miscellaneous and Scrapbooks.
Organization
Series I: Correspondence.
Arranged by subject and within each subject folder the papers are chronological. Some letters will refer to such things as bills or insurance policies, in which case the document referred to will be found in the box containing that type of document. Pictures of many of the rides and amusements mentioned in the letters can be found in the series on photography or the folders containing brochures.
Series II: Legal Documents.
Contains several folders of material on accidents that occurred at Ocean View and suits brought about by the injured parties. In these cases all documents and correspondence relating to each case have been clipped together. This is to make research of the accident cases simpler. Legal documents also include contracts, insurance forms, and lease agreements.
Series III: Financial Papers.
Contains all bills and receipts. In most cases they have simply been arranged in chronological order rather than subject. VEPCO and C & P bills are separated; as are automobile receipts. All bills are together preceding the receipts. In some cases it is difficult to determine whether a document should be termed "bill" or "receipt".
Series IV: Printed Materials.
Includes brochures, flyers, advertisements, news releases, and news clippings, and schedules of events.
Series V: Photographs.
Most of the photographs are of entertainment groups that performed at Ocean View, or who wished to perform at Ocean View and sent photos with their ads. Some are of special events at the park and one folder contains a group of color snapshots of the Park.
Series VI: Miscellaneous.
Includes items on the construction of the bathhouse, the movie "Roller Coaster" filmed at the amusement park, documents relating to the fire of November 8, 1964, sketches and architectural drawings, tickets, and articles relating to amusement parks, and Dudley Cooper.
Series VII:Scrapbooks.
Scrapbooks of news paper clippings and mementos documenting the history of Ocean View Amusement Park, dating from 1948-1967.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Accidents and Injuries 1944-1948 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Accidents and Injuries 1952 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Accidents and Injuries 1953-1954 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Accidents and Injuries 1955-1956 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Accidents and Injuries 1957-1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Accidents and Injuries 1967-1975 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Acts and Shows 1943-1951 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Acts and Shows Jan-Apr 1952 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Acts and Shows May-Nov 1952 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Acts and Shows 1953-1954 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Acts and Shows 1955-1957 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Acts and Shows 1958-1967 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Acts and Shows 1968-1970 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Acts and Shows Jan-May 1971 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Acts and Shows June-Dec 1971 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Acts and Shows 1972 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Acts and Shows 1973 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Acts and Shows, Indian Village 1961-1962 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Advertising 1943-1946 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Advertising 1947-1948 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advertising Feb-Mar 1952 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Advertising Apr-Oct 1952 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Advertising 1953-1957 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Advertising Jan-Nov 1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Advertising 1963-1965 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Advertising 1966-1975 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Banks 1943-1975 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Boats 1949-1953 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Boats 1954-1955 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bus and Taxi Service 1946-1956 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 11)
  - City and Goverment 1942-1947 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 12)
  - City and Goverment 1948-1953 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 13)
  - City and Goverment 1954-1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 14)
  - City and Goverment 1963-1975 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Comments on Ocean View 1943-1978 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Concessions 1943-1977 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Construction and Repairs 1943-1948 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Construction and Repairs 1950-1958 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Construction and Repairs 1965-1970 (Box-folder Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Contibutions 1953-1971 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibits and Special Equipment 1943-1951 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Exhibits and Special Equipment 1952-1953 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Exhibits and Special Equipment 1954-1967 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fireworks 1945-1947 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fireworks 1948-1958 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fireworks 1963-1975 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Free Passes and Gifts 1944-1946 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Free Passes and Gifts 1947-1948 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Free Passes and Gifts 1952-1968 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Insurance 1943-1948 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Insurance 1949-1952 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Insurance 1953 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Insurance 1954-1956 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Insurance 1957 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Insurance 1958 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Insurance 1959-1963 (Box-folder Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Insurance 1964 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Insurance Jan-Feb 1965 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Insurance Mar 1965 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Insurance Apr-Oct 1965 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Insurance Apr-Oct 1965 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Insurance 1966-1967 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Insurance 1968-1975 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Leases 1942-1968 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1942-1971 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 8)
  - National Association of Amusement Parks 1943-1965 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Navy and Shore Patrol 1956-1971 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Personal 1945-1958 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Personnel 1943-1966 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Rides 1941-1946 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rides 1947-1948 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Rides 1951-1958 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Rides 1967-1974 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Special Events 1948-1970 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Subscriptions 1952-1969 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Taxes 1943-1974 (Box-folder Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Telegrams 1943-1948 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Telegrams 1952-1970 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Utilities 1943-1948, 1966 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 3)
- Legal Documents
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1948-1955 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1956 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1957 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1958-1964 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1965 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1966 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1967 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1968 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Accidents and Court Cases 1969-1972 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Contracts 1943-1947 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Contracts 1952-1958 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Contracts 1963-1969 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Contracts 1970-1974 (Box-folder Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Insurance Forms 1945-1947 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Insurance Forms 1948 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Insurance Forms 1949 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Insurance Forms 1951-1952 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Insurance Forms 1953-1955 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Insurance Forms 1956 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Insurance Forms 1957-1958 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Insurance Forms 1964 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Insurance Forms 1966 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Insurance Forms 1967-1969 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Insurance Forms 1970-1974 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Leases and Rentals 1943 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Leases and Rentals 1944-1945 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Leases and Rentals 1946 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Leases and Rentals 1947 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Leases and Rentals 1948 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Leases and Rentals 1950-1959 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Music Licenses 1967-1968 (Box-folder Box 6, Folder 18)
- Financial Documents
  - Balance Sheets 1943 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Balance Sheets 1944-1945 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Balance Sheets 1946 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Balance Sheets 1947-1948 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Balance Sheets 1951-1954 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Balance Sheets 1958 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Balance Sheets 1963-1966 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Bank Receipts 1947-1948 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Bank Receipts 1951-1955 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Bank Receipts 1956-1959 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Bank Receipts 1964-1966 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Bank Receipts 1967 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Bank Receipts 1968-1969 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Bank Receipts 1970 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Bank Receipts 1971 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Bank Receipts 1972-1974 (Box-folder Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Bank Receipts 1975 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Bank Deposit Books 1953-1975 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Bills 1944-1948 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Bills 1951-1952 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bills 1953 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Bills 1955-1956 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Bills 1957 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Bills 1958 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Bills 1963-1975 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Bills, VEPCO, and C&P 1951-1968 (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Receipts-Airline Tickets (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Receipts-Automobile (I) (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Receipts-Automobile (II) (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Receipts-Automobile (III) (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Receipts-Automobile (IV) (Box-folder Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Receipts-Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Receipts-Taxes (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 2)
- Printed Material
  - Advertising Copy - Radio and TV 1952-1957 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Brochures - Acts (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Brochures - Norfolk (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Brochures - Ocean View (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Brochures - Rides and Equipment (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Brochures - Tidewater Virginia (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Flyers (I) (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Flyers (II) (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Newsclippings re. Nov 1964 Fire at Ocean View Amusement Park Nov 1964 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Newsclippings re. Closing of the Park 1978 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Newsclippings 1943-1963 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Newsclippings 1968 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Newsclippings 1969 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 15)
  - News Releases 1970 (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters-Virginia Transit Company;National Ballroom Operators Association (Box-folder Box 9, Folder 17)
  - News Releases 1952-1954 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 1)
  - News Releases 1955 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 2)
  - News Releases 1956 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 3)
  - News Releases 1957 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 4)
  - News Releases 1958 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 5)
  - News Releases 1968 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 6)
  - News Releases 1969 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 7)
  - News Releases 1970 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 8)
  - News Releases 1976 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Postcards (I) (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Postcards (II) (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Posters and Handbills (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Schedules of Events 1952-1970 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Schedules of Events 1971-1976 (Box-folder Box 10, Folder 14)
- Photographic Collection
  - Animal Acts (I) - Szymanski's Chimps (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Animal Acts (II) - Dog Acts (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Animal Acts (III) including poster (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 3)
  - High Wire Acts (I) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 4)
  - High Wire Acts (II)- Lovely Miss Rachel (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 5)
  - High Wire Acts (III) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 6)
  - High Wire Acts (IV) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 7)
  - High Wire Acts (V)- Capt. Eddie Sky-Thriller (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 8)
  - High Wire Acts (VI) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 9)
  - High Wire Acts (VII) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 10)
  - High Wire Acts (VIII) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 11)
  - High Wire Acts (IX)- The Fearless Bauers (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 12)
  - High Wire Acts (X) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 13)
  - High Wire Acts (XI) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 14)
  - High Wire Acts (XII)- The Rodriques Brothers (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 15)
  - High Wire Acts (XIII)- Miss Olga (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 16)
  - High Wire Acts (XIV) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 17)
  - High Wire Acts (XV) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 18)
  - High Wire Acts (XVI)- Erik Golden Boy of the High Wire (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 19)
  - High Wire Acts (XVII) (Box-folder Box 11, Folder 20)
  - High Wire Acts (XVIII) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 1)
  - High Wire Acts (XIX)- Trio Angelos (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 2)
  - High Wire Acts (XX) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 3)
  - High Wire Acts (XXI) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 4)
  - High Wire Acts (XXII) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Indian Village (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Juggling and Balancing Acts (I) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Juggling and Balancing Acts (II)- The Juggling Chef Pago (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Juggling and Balancing Acts (III) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Juggling and Balancing Acts (IV) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Magic Acts (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Trampoline Acts (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Acts (I) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Acts (II) (Box-folder Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park (I) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park (II) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park (III) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park (IV) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park (V) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park (VI) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park-Lady Buxom Contest Photos (I) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park-Lady Buxom Contest Photos (II) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park-Lady Buxom Contest Photos (III) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Ocean View Amusement Park-Lady Buxom Contest Photos (IV) (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Displays (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Box-folder Box 13, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous
  - Architectural Drawings (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Articles re. Amusement Parks (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Article re. Dudley Cooper (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Article for Warner Twyford (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Bath House Construction (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Cost Estimates re. Fire Novmember 8, 1964 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Electrical Damages Due to Fire November 8, 1964 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Movie-"Roller Coaster" 1976 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Prices-Rides (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Questionnaire-Ocean View Park 1968 (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Schedule of Insurance (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Sketches-Ocean View Amusement Park Sign (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Tickets (Box-folder Box 14, Folder 13)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook 1948-1949 (Oversize Oversize, Box 15)
  - Scrapbook 1949-1952 (Oversize Oversize, Box 15)
  - Scrapbook 1953-55 (Oversize Oversize, Box 16)
  - Scrapbook 1954 (Oversize Oversize, Box 16)
  - Scrapbook 1955-1956 (Oversize Oversize, Box 16)
  - Scrapbook 1960 (Oversize Oversize, Box 17)
  - Scrapbook 1963 (Oversize Oversize, Box 17)
  - Scrapbook 1964 (Oversize Oversize, Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 1965 (Oversize Oversize, Box 18)
  - Scrapbook 1966-1967 (Oversize Oversize, Box 19)